<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>
                    Nightwood Georeferenced
                </title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>(Information about distribution of the
                    resource)</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>(Information about source from which the resource derives)</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <!-- STATEMENT OF BEST PRACTICES FOR GEOREFERENCE MARKUP. In the tradition of surface reading, geographic references are tagged based on the geographic description given by the text. Strictly geo-locating spans on text based only on the description offered (including indirect geographic references), the markup includes ambiguous locations, historical locations, and imaginary places. -->
            
            <p>
            
            <!-- BOW DOWN -->
            
            <!-- Although Felix's birth likely takes place indoors, this description situates it in concert with the landscape outside. -->
            
            <span from="Field in Vienna">
                Turning upon this field, which shook to the clater of morning horses in the street beyond, with the gross splendour of a general saluting the flag, she named him Felix, thrust him from her, and died.
            </span>
            
            <span from="The Prater, Vienna">
                Then walking in the Prater he had been seen carrying in a conspicuously clenched fist the exquisite handkerchief of yellow and black linen that varied aloud of the ordinance of 1468
            </span>
            
            <span from="Corso, Rome">
                Guido's race should run in the Corso for the amusement of the Christian populace, while ladies of noble birth, sitting upon spines too refined for rest, arose from their seats, and, with the red-gowned cardinals and the Monsignori, applauded
                with that cold yet hysterical abandon of a people that is at once unjust and happy, the very Pope himself shaken down from his hold on heaven with the laughter of a man who forgoes his angels that he may recapture the beast.
            </span>
            
            <span from="The Prater, Vienna">
                He had walked, hot, incautious and damned, his eyelids quivering over the thick eyeballs, black with the pain of a participation
            </span>
              
            <span from="Piazza Montanara, Rome">
                that cry running the Piazza Montanara long ago, 'Roba vecchia!'--the degradation by which his people had survived.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Rome">
                When Hedvig came upon his black and yellow handkerchiefs he had said that they were to remind him that one branch of his family had bloomed in Rome.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Vienna">
                In the Vienna of Volkbein's day there were few trades that welcomed Jews
            </span>
            
            <span from="Guido's house, The Prater">
               a house in the Inner City, to the north, overlooking the Prater, a house that, large, dark and imposing, became a fantastic museum of their encounter.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Guido's house, the Prater">
                The long rococo halls, giddy with plush and whorled designs in gold, were peopled with Roman. fragments, white and disassociated; a runner's leg, the chilly half-turned head of a matron stricken at the bosom, the blind bold sockets of the eyes given a pupil by every shifting shadow so that what they looked upon was an act of the sun. The great salon was of walnut. Over the fireplace hung impressive copies of the Medici shield and, beside them, the Austrian bird.
                Three massive pianos (Hedvig had played the waltzes of her time with the masterly stroke of a man, in the tempo of her blood, rapid and rising--that quick mannerliness of touch associated with the playing of the Viennese, who, though pricked with the love of rhythm, execute its demands in the duelling manner) sprawled over the thick dragon's-blood pile of rugs from Madrid. The study harboured two rambling desks in rich and bloody wood. Hedvig had liked things in twos and threes. Into the middle arch of each desk silver-headed brads had been hammered to form a lion, a bear, a ram, a dove, and in their midst a flaming torch. The design was executed under the supervision of Guido who, thinking on the instant, claimed it as the Volkhein field, though it turned out to be a bit of heraldry long since in decline beneath the papal frown. The full length windows (a French touch that Guido thought handsome) overlooking the park were curtained in native velvets and stuffs from Tunis, and the Venetian blinds were of that peculiarly sombre shade of red so loved by the Austrians. Against the panels of oak that reared themselves above the long table and up to the curving ceiling hung life-sized portraits of Guido's claim to father and mother. The lady was a sumptuous Florentine with bright sly eyes and overt mouth. Great puffed and pearled sleeves rose to the pricked-eared paintings of the stiff lace about the head, conical and braided. The deep accumulation of dress fell about her in grained shadows, the train, rambling through a vista of primitive trees, was carpet-thick. She seemed to be expecting a bird. The gentleman was seated precariously on a charger. He seemed not so much to have mounted the animal, as to be about to descend upon him. The blue of an Italian sky lay between the saddle and the buff of the tightened rump of the rider. The charger had been caught by the painter in the execution of a falling arc, the mane lifted away in a dying swell; the tail forward and in, between thin bevelled legs. The gentleman's dress was a baffling mixture of the Romantic and the Religious, and in the cradling crook of his left arm he carried a plumed hat, crown out. The whole conception might have been a Mardi Gras whim. The gentleman's head, stuck on at a three-quarter angle, had a remarkable resemblance to Guido Volkbein, the same sweeping Cabalistic line of nose, the features seasoned and warm save where the virgin blue of the eyeballs curved out of the lids as if another medium than that of sight had taken its stand beneath that flesh. There was no interval in the speed of that stare, endless and objective. The likeness was accidental. Had anyone cared to look into the matter they would have discovered these canvases to be reproductions of two intrepid and ancient actors. Guido had found them in some forgotten and dusty corner and had purchased them when he had been sure that he would need an alibi for the blood.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Paris">
                In nineteen hundred and twenty he was in Paris (his blind eye had kept him out of the army), still spatted, still wearing his cutaway, bowing, searching, with quick pendulous movements, for the correct thing to which to pay tribute: the right street, the right cafe, the right building, the right vista. In restaurants he bowed slightly to anyone who looked as if he might be 'someone', making the bend so imperceptible that the surprised person might think he was merely adjusting his stomach.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Prague">
                The more amiable actresses of Prague,
            </span>
            
            <span from="Vienna">
                Vienna,
            </span>
            
            <span from="Hungary">
                Hungary, 
            </span>
            
            <span from="Germany">
                Germany, 
            </span>
            
            <span from="France">
               France
            </span>
            
            <span from="Italy">
               Italy
            </span>
            
            <span from="Musee Carnavalet">
                He moved with a humble hysteria among the decaying brocades and laces of the Carnavalet; he loved that old and documented splendour with something of the love of the lion for its tame
            </span>
            
            <span from="Le Cirque Metropole">
                The emotional spiral of the circus, taking its flight from the immense disqualification of the public, rebounding from its illimitable hope, produced in Felix longing and disquiet. The circus was a loved thing that he could never touch, therefore never know. The people of the theatre and the ring were for him as dramatic and as monstrous as a consignment on which he could never bid.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Berlin">
                Frau Mann, then in Berlin
            </span>
            
            <span from="Berlin">
                Berlin is sometimes very nice at night, nicht wahr?
            </span>
            
            <span from="Le Cirque Metropole">
                Now I am thinking of Nikka, the nigger who used to fight the bear in the Cirque de Paris. There he was, crouching all over the arena without a stitch on, except an ill-concealed loin cloth all abulge as if with a deep sea catch, tattooed from head to heel with all the ameuhlement of depravity! Garlanded with rosebuds and hack-work of the devil-was he a sight to see! Though he couldn't have done a thing (and I know what I am talking about in spite of all that has been said about the black boys) if you had stood him in a gig-mill for a week, though (it's said) at a stretch it spelled Desdemona. Well then, over his belly was an angel from Chartres, on each buttock, half public, half private, a quotation from the book of magic, a confirmation of the Jansenist theory, I'm sorry to say and here to say it. Across his knees, I give you my word, "I" on one and on the other, "can", put those together! Across his chest, beneath a beautiful caravel in full sail, two clasped hands, the wrist bones fretted with point lace. On each bosom an arrow-speared heart, each with different initials but with equal drops of blood; and running into the arm-pit, all down one side, the word said by Prince Arthur Tudor, son of King Henry the Seventh...The legs...were devoted
                entirely to vine work, topped by the swart rambler rbse copied from the coping of the Hamburg house of Rothschild. Over his dos, believe it or not and I shouldn't, a terse account in early monkish script---called by some people indecent, by others Gothic--
            </span>
            
            <span from="Paris">
                of the really deplorable condition of Paris before hygiene was introduced, and nature had its way up to the knees.
            </span>
                
            <span from="Le Cirque Metropole">
                And just above what you mustn't mention, a bird flew carrying a streamer on which was incised, "Garde tout!" I asked him why all this barbarity; he answered he loved beauty and would have it about him.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Vienna">
                Are you acquianted with Vienna?
            </span>
            
            <span from="Vienna">
                Vienna...the bed into which the common people climb, docile with toil, and out of which the nobility fling themselves, ferocious with dignity...I remember young Austrian boys going to school, flocks of quail they were, sitting out their recess in different spots in the sun, rosy-cheeked, bright-eyed, with damp rosy mouths, smelling of the herd childhood, facts of history glimmering in their minds like sunlight, soon to be lost, soon to be forgotten, degraded into proof.
            </span>
            
            <span from="The British Museum">
                look up the manuscripts in the British Museum
            </span>
            
            <span from="Clermont-Ferrand--Place de La Victoire 63000">
                go to the Cathedral of Clermont-Ferrand
            </span>
            
            <span from="Musee Cluny">
                I didn't stop until I found myself spang in the middle of the Musee de Cluny, clutching the rack.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Unter den Linden, Berlin">
                Let us go to Heinrich's, I always do when it's snowing. He mixes the drinks stronger then, and he's a good customer, he always takes in the show...Where is thy Heinrich?...Go down Unter den Linden
            </span>
            
            <!-- This cafe's location in Berlin remains indeterminate. -->
            
            <span from="cafe in Berlin">
                Seated in the warmth of the favoured cafe, the doctor, unwinding his scarf
            </span>
            
            <span from="les Pyrenees">
                She used to wheel herself through the Pyrenees on a board
            </span>
            
            <!-- LA SMONAMBULE-->
            
            <span from="Doctor's house">
                Close to the church of St. Sulpice, around the corner in the rue Servandoni, lived the doctor.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Place St Sulpice">
                His small slouching figure was a feature of the Place.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                the Cafe de la Mairie du VIe
            </span>
            
            <span from="Place St Sulpice">
                This relatively small square, through which tram lines ran in several directions, bounded on the one side by the church and on the other by the court, was the doctor's 'city'.
                What he could not find here to answer to his needs, could be found in the narrow streets that ran into it. Here he had been seen ordering details for funerals in the parlour with its black broadcloth curtains and mounted pictures of hearses; buying holy pictures and petits Jesus in the boutique displaying vestments and flowering candles.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Mairie du Luxembourg">
                He had shouted down at least one judge in the Mairie du Luxembourg after a dozen cigars had failed to bring about his ends.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Foire St Germain">
                He walked, pathetic and alone, among the pasteboard booths of the Foire St. Germain when for a time its imitation castles squatted in the square. He was seen coming at a smart pace down the left side of the church to go into Mass; bathing in the holy water stoup as if he were its single and beholden bird, pushing aside weary French maids and local tradespeople with the impatience of a soul in physical stress.
            </span>
     
            <span from="Eglise St Sulpice">
                Sometimes, late at night,
            </span>
     
            <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                before turning into the Cafe de la Mairie de VI"
            </span>
            
            <span from="Eglise St Sulpice">
                he would be observed staring up at the huge towers of the church which rose into the sky, unlovely but reassuring, running a thick warm finger around his throat, where, in spite of its customs, his hair surprised him, lifting along his back and creeping up over his collar.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Fontaine St Sulpice">
                Standing small and insubordinate, he would watch the basins of the fountain loosing their skirts of water in a ragged and flowing hem, sometimes crying to a man's departing shadow: 'Aren't you the beauty!'
            </span>
            
            <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                To the Cafe de la Mairie du VIe he brought Felix,
            </span>
            
            <span from="Paris">
                who turned up in Paris some weeks after
            </span>
            
            <span from="Berlin">
                the encounter in Berlin.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Vienna">
                'In 1685,' the Baron said, with dry humour, 'the Turks brought coffee into Vienna, and from that day Vienna, like a woman, had one impatience, something she liked.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Austria">
                Austria and tea could never go together.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Austria">
                Austria and tea could never go together.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Hotel Recamier">
                the Hotel Recamier
            </span>
            
            <span from="Hotel Recamier">
                On the second landing of the hotel (it was one of those middle-class hostelries which can be found in almost any corner of Paris, neither good nor bad, but so typical that it might have been moved every night and not have been out of place) a door was open, exposing a red-carpet floor, and at the further end, two narrow windows overlooking the square.
                In a bed, surrounded by a confusion of potted plants, exotic palms and cut flowers, faintly oversung by the notes of unseen birds, which seemed to have been forgotten--left without the usual silencing cover, which, like cloaks on funeral urns, are cast over their cages at night by good house-wives)--half flung off the support of cushions from which, in a moment of threatened conscious- ness she had turned her head, lay the young woman, heavy and dishevelled.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                Cafe de la Mairie du VIe,' said the doctor
            </span>
            
            <span from="Hotel Recamier, Outside">
                Descending into the street, the doctor, desiring 'one last before bed' directed his steps back to the cafe.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                With a roar the steel blind came down over the window of the Cafe de la Mairie du VIe.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Hotel Recamier">
                Felix, carrying two volumes on the life of the Bourbons, called the next day at the Hdtel Recamier. Miss Vote was not in.
            </span>
                
            <!-- The doctor is likely turning onto the rue Bonaparte from la Place St Sulpice. -->
            
            <span from="Rue Bonaparte">
                turning the corner of the rue Bonaparte, he ran into her.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Hotel Recamier">
                Removed from her setting-the plants that had surrounded her, the melancholy red velvet of the chairs and the curtains, the sound, weak and nocturnal, of the bird
            </span>
            
            <span from="Jardin du Luxembourg">
                She suggested that they should walk together in the gardens of the Luxembourg toward which her steps had been directed when he addressed her. They walked in the bare chilly gardens and Felix was happy.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Credit Lyonnais">
                He told her he had a post in the Credit Lyonnais
            </span>
            
            <!-- The location of the antique shop is unclear, but likely between le Pont Royal and le Pont des Saints-Peres on the left bank. -->
            <span from="antique shop facing the Seine">
                Pricing a small tapestry in an antique shop facing the Seine, he saw Robin reflected in a door mirror of a back room, dressed in a heavy brocaded gown which time had stained in places, in others split, yet which was so voluminous that there were yards enough to refashion.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Vienna">
                He took her first to Vienna. To reassure himself he showed her all the historic buildings. He kept saying to himself that sooner or later, in this garden or that palace, she would suddenly be moved as he was moved. Yet it seemed to him that he too was a sightseer. He tried to explain to her what Vienna had been before the war; what it must have been before he was born; yet his memory was confused and hazy, and he found himself repeating what he had read, for it was what he knew best. With methodic anxiety he took her over the city. He said, 'You are a Baronin now.' He spoke to her in German as she ate the heavy Schnitzel and dumplings, clasping her hand about the thick handle of the beer mug. He said: 'Das Leben ist ewig, darin liegt seine Schonheit.'
            </span>
            
            <span from="Imperial Palace, Vienna">
                They walked before the Imperial Palace in a fine hot sun that fell about the clipped hedges and the statues warm and clear.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Kammergarten: Schonbrunn Palace, Vienna">
                He went into the Kammergarten with her and talked, 
            </span>
            
            <span from="Gloriette: Schonbrunn Palace, Vienna">
                and on into the Gloriette, and sat on first one bench, and then another. Brought up short, he realized that he had been hurrying from one to the other as if they were orchestra chairs, as if he himself were trying not to miss anything;
            </span>
            
            <span from="Kammergarten: Schonbrunn Palace, Vienna">
            now, at the extremity of the garden, he was aware that he had been anxious to see every tree, every statue at a different angle.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Hotel in Vienna">
                In their hotel, she went to the window and pulled aside the heavy velvet hangings, threw down the bolster that Vienna uses against the wind at the ledge, and opened the window, though the night air was cold.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Paris">
                Felix turned about and re-entered Paris
            </span>
            
            <!-- The account of Robin's wandering begins here. -->
            
            <!-- The location(s) for Robin's wandering is extremely indeterminate. This high geographic indeterminacy may suggest that the act of wandering eclipses any attempt to situate this span of text within a set of stable geographic locations. This span describes journeys, rather than geography. -->
            <span from="Europe--unknown wandering">
                strangely aware of some lost land in herself, she took to going out; wandering the countryside; to train travel, to other cities, alone and engrossed. Once, not having returned for three days, and Felix nearly beside himself with terror, she walked in late at night and said that she had been half-way to Berlin.
            </span>
            
            <span from="St Julien le Pauvre">
                St. Julien le Pauvre
            </span>
            
            <span from="Eglise St Germain des Pres">
                the church of St. Germain des Pres
            </span>
            
            <span from="Eglise Ste Clothilde">
                Ste. Clothilde
            </span>
            
            <span from="Catherdrale Alexandre Nevsky">
                Even on the cold tiles of the Russian church, in which there is no pew, she knelt alone, lost and conspicuous, her broad shoulders above her neighbours, her feet large and as earthly as the feet of a monk.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Couvent de l'Adoration Perpetuelle">
                She strayed into the rue Picpus, into the gardens of the convent of L'Adoration Perpetuelle. She talked to the nuns and they, feeling that they were looking at someone who would never be able to ask for, or receive, mercy, blessed her in their hearts and gave her a sprig of rose from the bush. They showed her where Jean Valjean had kept his rakes, and where the bright little ladies of the pension canie to quilt their covers; and Robin smiled, taking the spray, and looked down at the tomb of Lafayette and thought her unpeopled thoughts. Kneeling in the chapel, which was never without a nun going over her beads, Robin, trying to bring her mind to this abrupt necessity, found herself worrying about her height. Was she still growing?
            </span>
            
            <span from="Couvent de l'Adoration Perpetuelle">
                Leaning her childish face and full chin on the shelf of the prie-Dieu, her eyes fixed, she laughed, out of some hidden capacity, some lost subterran- ean humour; as it ceased, she leaned still further forward in a swoon, waking and yet heavy, like one in sleep.
            </span>
        
        <!-- End account of Robin's wandering -->
            
            <!-- This locating is extremely indeterminate. Again, it refers to a series of compossible locations, rather than any stable geographic area. -->
            
            <span from="Cafe in Paris, indeterminate">
                Sometimes coming into a cafe he would creep out again, because she stood before the bar--sometimes laughing, but more often silent, her head bent over her glass, her hair swinging; and about her people of every sort.
            </span>
            
            <span from="quartier latin">
                When she was seen again in the quarter, it was with Nora Flood
            </span>
            
            <span from="America">
                The doctor said: 'In America, that's where Nora lives.
            </span>
            
            <!-- NIGHT WATCH -->
            
            <span from="Nora's House, USA">
                The strangest 'salon' in America was Nora's. Her house was couched in the centre of a mass of tangled grass and weeds. Before it fell into Nora's hands the property had been in the same family two hundred years. It had its own burial ground, and a decaying chapel in which stood in tens and tens mouldering psalm books, laid down some fifty years gone in a flurry of forgiveness and absolution.
                It was the 'paupers' salon, for poets, radicals, beggars, artists, and people in love; for Catholics, Protestants, Brahmins, dabblers in black magic and medicine; all these could be seen sitting about her oak table before the huge fire, Nora listening, her hand on her hound, the firelight throwing her shadow and his high against the wall.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Nora's House, USA">
                Nora's house...in her ruined gardens where she had been wax in every work of nature.
            </span>
            
            <span from="The Deckman Circus">
                The Denckman circus, which she kept in touch with even when she was not working with it (some of its people were visitors to her house), came into New York in the fall of 1923. Nora went alone. She came into the circle of the ring, taking her place in the front row.
                Clowns in red, white and yellow, with the traditional smears on their faces, were rolling over the sawdust, as if they were in the belly of a great mother where there was yet room to play. A black horse, standing on trembling hind legs that shook in apprehension of the raised front hooves, his beautiful ribboned head pointed down and toward the trainer's whip, pranced slowly, the foreshanks flickering to the flickering whip. Tiny dogs ran about trying to look like horses, then in came the elephants. A girl sitting beside Nora took out a cigarette and lit it; her hands shook and Nora turned to look at her; she looked at her suddenly because the animals, going around and around the ring, all but climbed over at that point. They did not seem to see the girl, but as their dusty eyes moved past, the orbit of their light seemed to turn on her. At that moment Nora turned.
                The great cage for the lions had been set up, and the lions were walking up and out of their small strong boxes into the arena. Ponderous and furred they came, their tails laid down across the floor, dragging and heavy, making the air seem full of withheld strength. Then as one powerful came to the turn of the bars, exactly opposite the girl, she turned her furious great head with its yellow eyes afire and went down, her paws thrust through the bars and, as she regarded the girl, as if a river were falling behind impassable heat, her eyes flowed in tears that never reached the surface. At that the girl rose straight up. Nora took her hand. 'Let's get out of here!' the girl said, and still holding her hand Nora took her out.
                In the lobby Nora said, 'My name is Nora Flood,' and she waited. After a pause the girl said, 'I'm Robin Vote.' She looked about her distractedly. 'I don't want to be here.' But it was all she said; she did not explain where she wished to be.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Nora's house, USA">
                Nora closed her house.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Munich">
                Munich
            </span>
            
            <span from="Vienna">
                Vienna
            </span>
            
            <span from="Budapest">
                Budapest
            </span>
            
            <span from="Paris">
                into Paris.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Nora's house, Paris">
                Nora bought an apartment in the rue du Cherche-Midi. Robin had chosen it. Looking from the long windows one saw a fountain figure, a tall granite woman bending forward with lifted head, one hand was held over the pelvic round as if to warn a child who goes incautiously.
                In  the passage of their lives together every object in the garden, every item in the house, every word they spoke, attested to their mutual love, the combining of their humours. There were circus chairs, wooden horses bought from a ring of an old merry-go-round, venetian chandeliers from the Flea Fair, stage-drops from Munich, cherubim from Vienna, ecclesiastical hangings from Rome, a spinet from England, and a miscellaneous collection of music boxes from many countries; such was the museum of their encounter, as Felix's hearsay house had been testimony of the age when his father had lived with his mother.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Nora's house, Paris">
                Sometimes Nora would sing them after Robin...the song would be taken up again, from an inner room where Robin, unseen, gave back an echo of her unknown life more nearly tuned to its origin. Often the song would stop altogether, until unthinking, just as she was leaving the house, Robin would break out again in anticipation, changing the sound from a reminiscence to an expectation.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Nora's house, Paris">
                Yet sometimes, going about the house, in passing each other, they would fall into an agonized embrace, looking into each other's face, their two heads in their four hands, so strained together that the space that divided them seemed to be thrusting them apart.
            </span>
            
            <!-- Using the references in this span of text and elsewhere, Nora's street address can be approximated to 88 rue du Cherche-Midi -->
            
            <span from="Nora's house, Paris">
                Looking out into the fading sun of the winter sky, against which a little tower rose just outside the bedroom window, Nora would tabulate by the sounds of Robin dressing the exact progress of her toilet; chimes of cosmetic bottles and cream jars; the faint perfume of hair heated under the electric curlers
            </span>
            
            <span from="Nora's house, Paris">
                Nora stayed at home, lying awake or sleeping
            </span>
            
            <!-- The precise location of the mascaron remains unkonw, thought its proximity to a cluster of Cafes suggests the location is near St Germain des Pres. --> 
            
            <span from="Mascaron, Boulevard St Germain">
                Once out in the open Robin walked in a formless meditation, her hands thrust into the sleeves of her coat, directing her steps toward that night life that was a known measure between Nora and the cafes...She walked with raised head, seeming to look at every passer-by, yet her gaze was anchored in anticipation and regret. A look of anger, intense and hurried, shadowed her face and drew her mouth down as she neared her company; yet as her eyes moved over the facades of the buildings,searching for the sculptured head that both she and Nora loved (a Greek head with shocked protruding eyeballs, for which the tragic mouth seemed to pour forth tears,) a quiet joy radiated from her own eyes; for this head was remembrance of Nora and her love, making the anticipation of the people she was to meet set and melancholy. So, without knowing she would do so, she took the turn that brought her into this particular street. If she was diverted, as was sometimes the case, by the interposition of a company of soldiers, a wedding or a funeral, then by her agitation she seemed a part of the function to the persons she stumbled against; as a moth by his very entanglement with the heat that shall be his extinction is associated with flame as a component part of its function. It was this characteristic that saved her from being asked too sharply 'where' she was going; pedestrians who had it on the point of their tongues, seeing her rapt and confused, turned instead to look at each other.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Mascaron, Boulevard St Germain">
                Looking at every couple as they passed, into every carriage and car, up to the lighted windows of the houses, trying to discover not Robin any longer, but traces of Robin, influences in her life (and those which were yet to be betrayed), Nora watched every moving figure for some gesture that might turn up in the movements made by Robin
            </span>
            
            <span from="Mascaron, Boulevard St Germain">
                avoiding the quarter where she knew her to be, where by her own movements the waiters, the people on the terraces might know that she had a part in Robin's life.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Nora's house, Paris">
                home, the interminable night would begin. Listening to the faint sounds from the street, every murmur from the garden, an unevolved and tiny hum that spoke of the progressive growth of noise that would be Robin coming home, Nora lay and beat her pillow without force, unable to cry, her legs drawn up. At times she would get up and walk, to make something in her life outside more quickly over; to bring Robin back by the very velocity of the beating of her heart. And walking in vain, suddenly she would sit down on one of the circus chairs that stood by the long window overlooking the garden, bend forward putting her hands between her legs, and begin to cry 'Oh God! Oh God! Oh God!' repeated so often that it had the effect of all words spoken in vain
            </span>
            
            <span from="Grandmother's house, dream">
                the top of a house, thatis, that last floor but one--this was her grandmother's room--an expansive, decaying splendour; yet somehow, though set with all the belongings of her grandmother, was as bereft as the nest of a bird which will not return. Portraits ofher great-uncle, Llewellyn, who died inthe Civil War, faded pale carpets, curtains that resembled columns from their time in stillness--a plume and ink well--the ink faded into the quill...the body of the house, as if from a scaffold...A disc of light, that seemed to come from someone or thing standing behind her and which was yet a shadow, shed a faintly luminous flow upon the upturned still face of Robin...the room was taboo...the further away went the floor below...the two ends of the building, stretching her apart...The chamber had never been her grandmother's, which was, on the contrary, the absolute opposite of any known room her grandmother had ever moved or lived in, was nevertheless saturated with the lost presence of her grandmother, who seemed in the continual process of leaving it
            </span>
            
            <span from="Grandmother's house, USA">
                at the corner of the house
            </span>
            
            <span from="Nora's house, Paris">
                looking out into the garden in the faint light of dawn, she saw a double shadow falling from the statue, as if it were multiplying, and thinking perhaps this was Robin, she called and was not answered. Standing motionless, straining her eyes, she saw emerge from the darkness the light of Robin's eyes, fear in them developing their luminosity until, by the intensity of their double regard, Robin's eyes and hers met. So they gazed at each other. As if that light had power to bring what was dreaded into the zone of their catastrophe, Nora saw the body of another woman swim up into the statue's obscurity, with head hung down, that the added eyes might not augment the illumination; her arms about Robin's neck, her body pressed to Robin's, her legs slackened in the hang of the embrace.
            </span>
            
            <!-- THE SQUATTER -->
            
            <!-- The precise location of Jenny's house remains unknown. However, but she does live just off les Champs (likely in the 16=th). Locating the Paris address for Henrietta Alice Metcalf, who inspired the character, may further resolve uncertainty here. -->
            
            <span from="Jenny's house">
                Her walls, her cupboards, her bureaux, were teeming with second-hand dealings with life. It takes a bold and authentic robber to get first-hand plunder. Someone else's marriage ring was on her finger; the photograph taken of Robin for Nora sat upon her table. The books in her library were other people's selections. She lived among her own things like a visitor to a room kept 'exactly as it was when-'. She tiptoed, even when she went to draw a bath, nervous and andante. She stopped, fluttering and febrile, before every object in her house. She had no sense of humour or peace or rest, and her own quivering uncertainty made even the objects which she pointed out to the company, as, 'My virgin from Palma', or, 'The left-hand glove of La Duse', recede into a distance of uncertainty, so that it was almost impossible for the onlooker to see them at all.
            </span>
            
            <span from="les Ambassadeurs">
                Perhaps at the Ambassadeurs (Jenny feared meeting Nora).
            </span>
            
            <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                Perhaps dinner in the Bois--(Jenny had the collective in-come four dead husbands could afford)--Robin would walk in, with the aggressive slide to the foot common to tall people, slurred in its accent by the hipless smoothness of her gait--her hands in her pockets, the trench coat with the belt hanging, scowling and reluctant. Jenny leaning far over the table, Robin far back, her legs thrust under her, to balance the whole backward incline of the body, and Jenny so far forward that she had to catch her small legs in the back rung of the chair, ankle out and toe in, not to pitch forward on the table--thus they presented the two halves of a movement that had, as in sculpture, the beauty and the absurdity of a desire that is in flower but that can have no burgeoning, unable to execute its destiny; a movement that can divulge neither caution nor daring, for the fundamental condition for completion was in neither of them; they were like Greek runners, with lifted feet but without the relief of the final command that would bring the foot down--eternally angry, eternally separated, in a cataleptic frozen gesture of abandon.
            </span>
            
            <span from="l'Opera Garnier">
                The meeting at the opera had not been the first, but Jenny, seeing the doctor in the promenoir, aware of his passion for gossip, knew she had better make it seem so
            </span>
                
            <span from="Jenny's house">
                On arriving at her house with the doctor and Robin, Jenny found several actresses awaiting her, two gentlemen, and the Marchesa de Spada, a very old rheumatic woman (with an antique spaniel, which suffered from asthma), who believed in the stars. There was talk about fate, and every hand in the room was searched and every destiny turned over and discussed. A little girl (Jenny called her niece, though she was no relation) sat at the far end of the room. She had been playing, but the moment Robin entered she ceased, and sat, her two small wax-like hands tender with the new life in them cupped up in her lap, under her long-lashed eyelids at no one else, as if she had become prematurely aware. This was the child Jenny spoke of later, when she called on Felix. The Marchesa remarked that everyone in the room had been going on from interminable sources since the world began, and would continue to reappear, but that there was one person who had come to the end of her existence and would return no more. As she spoke, she looked slyly at Robin, who was standing by the piano speaking to the child in an undertone; and at the Marchesa's words Jenny began to tremble slightly, so that every point of her upstanding hair--it stood about her head in a bush, virile and unlovely-quiyered. She began to pull herself along the enormous sofa towards the Marchesa, her legs under her, and suddenly she stood up.'Order the carriages!' she cried. 'Immediately! We will go driving, we need a little air!' She turned her back and spoke in agitation. 'Yes, yes,' she said, 'The carriages! It is so close in here!'
                'What carriages?' said the doctor, and he looked from one to the other. 'What carriages?' He could hear the maid unlocking the front door, calling out to the coachmen. He could hear the clear ringing sound of wheels drawn close to the curb and the muttered cries of a foreign voice. Robin turned around and said, a malign gentle smile on her mouth, 'Now she is in a panic, and we will have to do something.' She put her glass down and stood, her back to the room, her broad shoulders drawn up, and though she was drunk, there was a withdrawal in her movement, and a wish to be gone.
                'She will dress up now,' she said. She leaned back against the piano, pointing with the hand that held her glass.
            </span>
                
            <!-- The carraige ride begins here, with the span above introducing the journey. It is of note that the spans of text noticeably surpass the average length in this section, as character discourse and actions play a key role in the description of setting. -->
                
            <span from="Jenny's house, driveway">
                Jenny, cold with dread lest Robin should get into one of the other carriages with a tall slightly surprised English girl, seated herself in the farthest corner of the foremost fiacre and called, 'Here, here,' leaving the rest of the guests to dispose of themselves. The child, Sylvia, sat across from her, the ragged gray rug held in two clenched hands. There was a great deal of chattering and laughter, when to her horror Jenny saw that Robin was moving toward the second carriage in which the English girl had already seated herself. 'Ah no, no!' Jenny cried, and began beating the upholstery, sending up a cloud of dust. 'Come here,' she ·said in an anguished voice, as if it were the end of her life, 'Come here with me, both of you,' she added in a lowered and choking tone; and assisted by the doctor, Robin got in, the young Englishwoman, to Jenny's consternation, taking the seat by her side.
            </span>
            
            <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                'Where to but the woods, the sweet woods of Paris! Fais le tour du Bois!'
            </span>
                
                <!-- This location is just on the Champs, turning up from Jenny's street (likely just south in the 16th). -->
                
            <span from="Champs Elysees-carriage ride">
                slowly the three carriages, horse behind horse, moved out into the Champs Elysees.
            </span>
                
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne-carriage ride">
                    Jenny, with nothing to protect her against the night but her long Spanish shawl, which looked ridiculous over her flimsy hoop and bodice, a rug over her knees, had sunk back with, collapsed shoulders. With darting, incredible swiftness, her eyes went from one girl to the other, while the doctor, wondering how he had managed to get himself into the carriage which held three women and a child, listened to the faint laughter from the carriages behind, feeling, as he listened, a twinge of occult misery. 'Ah!' he said under his breath. 'Just the girl that God forgot.' Saying which, he seemed to be precipitated into the halls of justice, where he had suffered twenty-four hours. 'Oh, God help us,' he said, speaking aloud, at which the child turned slightly on her seat, her head, with large intelligent eyes directed toward him, which had he noticed, would have silenced him instantly
                    (for the doctor had a mother's reverence for childhood). 'What manner of man is it that has to adopt his brother's children to make a mother of himself, and sleeps with his brother's wife to get him a future--it's enough to bring down the black
                    curse of Kerry.'
                    'What?' said Jenny in a loud voice, hoping to effect a break in the whispered conversation between Robin and the English girl. The doctor turned up his coat collar.
                    'I was saying, madame, that by his own peculiar perversity God has made me a liar-'
                    'What, what is that you say?' demanded Jenny, her eyes still fixed on Robin so that her question seemed to be directed rather to that corner of the carriage than to the doctor.
                    'You see before you, madame,' he said, 'one who was created in anxiety. My father, Lord rest his soul, had no happiness of me from the beginning. When I joined the army he relented a little because he had a suspicion that possibly in that fracas which occasionally puts a son on the list of "not much left since", I might be damaged. After all, he had no desire to see my ways corrected with a round of buckshot. He came into me early in the dawn as I lay in my bed, to say that he forgave me, and that indeed he hoped to be forgiven; that he had never understood, but that he had, by much thought, by heavy reading, come back with love in his hand, that he was sorry, that he came to say so; that he hoped I could conduct myself like a soldier. For a moment he seemed to realize my terrible predicament: to be shot for man's meat, but to go down like a girl, crying in the night for her mother. So I got up in bed on my knees and crawled to the foot where he stood, and cast my arms about him and said, "No matter what you have done or thought, you were right, and there's nothing in my heart but love for you and respect."'
                    Jenny had shrunk into her rug and was not listening. Her eyes followed every movement of Robin's hand, which was laid now on the child's hand, now stroking her hair, the child smiling up into the trees.
                    'Oh,' said the doctor, 'for the love of God!'
                    Jenny began to cry slowly, the tears wet, warm, and sudden in the odd misery of her face. It made the doctor sad, with that unhappy yet pleasantly regrettable discomfort on which he usually launched his better meditations.
                    He remarked, and why he did not know, that by weeping she appeared like a single personality, who, by multiplying her tears, brought herself in-to the position of one who is seen twenty times in twenty mirrors-still only one, but many times distressed. Jenny began to weep outright.
                </span>
                
                <!-- It is of note that other quarters are given highly granular treatment, whereas "the lower parts of town" (likely the 15th) is glossed over entirely here. -->
                
                <span from="toward the lower parts of town">
                    As the initial soft weeping had not caught Robin's attention, now Jenny used the increase and the catching in her throat to attract her, with the same insistent fury one feels when trying to attract a person in a crowded room. The weeping became as accurate as the monotonous underplay in a score, in spite of the incapacity of her heart. The doctor, sitting now a little slumped forward, said, in an almost professional voice (they were now long past the pond and the park, and were circling back again, toward the lower parts of town), 'Love of woman for woman, what insane passion for unmitigated anguish and motherhood brought that into the mind?'
                    'Oh, Oh,' she said, 'Look at her!' She abruptly made a gesture toward Robin and the girl, as if they were no longer present, as if they were a vista passing out of view with the movement of the horses. 'Look, she brings love down to a level!' She hoped that Robin would hear.
                    'Ah!' he said. 'Love, that terrible thing!'
                    She began to beat the cushions with her doubled fist. 'What could you know about it? Men never know anything about it, why should they? But a woman should know--they are finer, more sacred; my love is sacred and my love is great!'
                    'Shut up,' Robin said, putting her hand on her knee. 'Shut up, you don't know what you are talking about. You talk all the time and you never know anything. It's such an awful weakness with you. Identifying yourself with God!' She was smiling, and the English breathing very quickly, lit a cigarette. The child remained speechless, as she had been for the duration of the drive, her head turned as if fixed, looking at Robin, and trying to hold her slight legs, that did not reach the floor, from shaking with the shaking of the carriage.
                    Then Jenny struck Robin, scratching and tearing in hysteria, striking, clutching and crying. Slowly the blood began to run down Robin's cheeks, and as Jenny struck repeatedly Robin began to go forward as if brought to the movement by the very blows themselves, as if she had no will, sinking down in the small carriage, her knees on the floor, her head forward as her arm moved upward in a gesture of defence; and as she sank, Jenny also, as if compelled to conclude the movement of the first blow, almost as something seen in retarded action, leaned forward and over, so that when the whole of the gesture was completed, Robin's hands were covered by Jenny's slight and bending breast, caught in between the bosom and the knees. And suddenly the child flung herself down on the seat, face outward, and said in a voice not suitable for a child, because it was controlled with terror: 'Let me go! Let me go! Let me go!'
                </span>
                
                <span from="rue du cherche-midi-carriage ride">
                    The carriage at this moment drew smartly up into the rue du Cherche-Midi. Robin jumped before the carriage stopped, but Jenny was close behind her
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house, Paris">
                    following her as far as the garden.
                </span>
                
                <span from="America">
                    a little later Jenny and Robin sailed for America.
                </span>
                
                <!-- WATCHMAN, WHAT OF THE NIGHT? -->
                
                
                <!-- Note how the description becomes inscreasingly focused on the doctor, before shifting to the discussion of the night. -->
                
               <span from="Doctor's house">
                   About three in the morning, Nora knocked at the little glass door of the concierge's loge, asking if the doctor was in. In the anger of broken sleep the concierge directed her to climb six flights, where at the top of the house, to the left, she would find him.
                   Nora took the stairs slowly. She had not known that the doctor was so poor. Groping her way she rapped, fumbling for the knob. Misery alone would have brought her, though she knew the late hours indulged in by her friend. Hearing his 'come in' she opened the door and for one second hesitated, so incredible was the disorder that met her eyes. The room was so small that it was just possible to walk sideways up to the bed, it was as if being condemned to the grave the doctor had decided to occupy it with the utmost abandon.
                   A  pile of medical books, and volumes of a miscellaneous order, reached almost to the ceiling, water-stained and covered with dust. Just above them was a very small barred window, the only ventilation. On a maple dresser, certainly not of European make, lay a rusty pair of forceps, a broken scalpel, half a dozen odd instruments that she could not place, a catheter, some twenty perfume bottles, almost empty, pomades, creams, rouges, powder boxes and puffs. From the half-open drawers of this chiffonier hung laces, ribands, stockings, ladies' underclothing and an abdominal brace, which gave the impression that the feminine finery had suffered venery. A swill-pail stood at the head of the bed, brimming with abominations. There was something appallingly degraded about the room, like the rooms in brothels, which give even the most innocent a sensation of having been accomplice; yet this room was also muscular, a cross between a chambre à coucher and a boxer's training camp. There is a certain belligerence in a room in which a woman has never set foot; every object seems to be battling its own compression-and there is a metallic odour, as of beaten iron in a smithy.
                   In the narrow iron bed, with its heavy and dirty linen sheets; lay the doctor in a woman's flannel night gown.
                   The doctor's head, with its over-large black eyes, its full gun-metal cheeks and chin, was framed in the golden semi-circle of a wig with long pendent curls that touched his shoulders, and falling back against the pillow, turned up the shadowy interior of their cylinders. He was heavily rouged and his lashes painted. It flashed into Nora's head: 'God, children know something they can't tell, they like Red Riding Hood and the wolf in bed!' But this thought, which was only the sensation of a thought, was of but a second's duration, as she opened the door; in the next, the doctor had snatched the wig from his head, and sinking down in the bed drew the sheets up over his breast. Nora said, as quickly as she could recover herself: 'Doctor, I have come to ask you to tell me everything you know about the night.' As she spoke, she wondered why she was so dismayed to have come upon the doctor at the hour when he had evacuated custom and gone back into his dress. The doctor said, 'You see that you can ask me anything,' thus laying aside both their embarrassments. She said to herself: 'Is not the gown the natural raiment of extremity? What nation, what religion, what ghost, what dream has not worn it--infants, angels, priests, the dead; why should not the doctor, in the grave dilemma of his alchemy, wear his dress?' She thought: 'He dresses to lie beside himself, who is so constructed that love, for him, can be only something special; in a room that giving back evidence of his occupancy, is as mauled as the last agony.' 'Have you ever thought of the night?' the doctor inquired with a little irony; he was extremely put out, having expected someone else, though his favourite topic, and one which he talked on whenever he had a chance, was the night. 'Yes,' said Nora, and sat down on the only chair. 'I've thought of it, but thinking about something you know nothing about does not help.'                 
               </span>
                
                <span from="Paris">
                    in Paris? When the streets were gall high with things you wouldn't have done for a dare's sake, and the way it was then; with the pheasants' necks and the goslings' beaks dangling against the hocks of the gallants, and not a pavement in the place, and everything gutters for miles and miles, and a stench to it that plucked you by the nostrils and you were twenty leagues out! The criers telling the price of wine to such good effect that the dawn saw good clerks full of piss and vinegar, and blood-letting in side streets where some wild princess in a night shift of velvet howled under a leech
               </span>
                
                <span from="Nymphenburg Palace, Germany">
                    not to mention the palaces of Nymphenburg echoing back
                </span>
                
                <span from="Vienna">
                    Vienna with the night trip of late kings letting water into plush cans and fine woodwork
                </span>
                
                <span from="Paris">
                    Let us take Paris for an instance
                </span>
                
                <span from="France">
                    and France for a fact.
                </span>
                
                <span from="French Nights">
                    French nights are those which all nations seek the world over
                </span>
                
                <span from="French Nights">
                    'I'm telling you of French nights at the moment,' the doctor went on, 'and why we all go into them.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Doctor's house">
                    'Oh, for God's sake!' the doctor said, 'give me the smelling salts.' She got up, looking among the debris on the stand. Inhaling, he pushed his head back into the pillow
                </span>
                
                <span from="Sodom and Gomorrah">
                    Was it at night that Sodom became Gomorrah? It was at night, I swear! A city given over to the shades, and that's why it has never been countenanced or understood to this day
                </span>
                
                <span from="Rome">
                    All through the night Rome went burning.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Rome">
                    Rome was the egg, but colour was the tread.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Redaction et Administration, 8 Rue Druout">
                    A European gets out of bed with a disorder that holds the balance. The layers of his deed can be traced back to the last leaf and the good slug be found creeping. L'Echo de Paris and his bed sheets were run off the same press. One may read in both the travail life has had with him-he reeks with the essential wit necessary to the "sale" of both editions, night edition and day.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Marseilles">
                    In the old days I was possibly a girl in Marseilles thumping the dock with a sailor
                </span>
                
                <span from="Place de la Bastille">
                    I haunt the pissoirs as naturally, in search of my man, as Highland Mary her cows down by the Dee--and by the Hobs of Hell, I've seen the same thing work in a  girl looking for her woman, but I'll bring that up later!
                </span>
                
                <span from="Place de la Bastille">
                    And do you think that those circular cottages have not brought me to great argument? Have you ever glanced at one when the night was well down, and seen it and what it looked like and resembled most, with its one coping and a hundred legs? A centipede. And you look down and choose your feet, and, ten to one, you find a bird with a light wing, or an old duck with a wooden knee, or something that has been mournful for years. What?
                </span>
                
                <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                    I've held argument with others at long tables all night through about the particular merits of one district over another for such things, of one cottage over another for such things. And do you suppose I was agreed with, and had any one any other one's ideas? There was as much disagreement as there might have been, had we all been selecting a new order of government. Jed would say North, and Jod would say South, and me sitting between them going mad because I am a doctor and a collector and a talker of Latin, and a sort of petropus of the twilight and a physiognomist that can't be flustered by the wrong feature on the right face
                </span>
                
                <span from="Place de la Bastille">
                    I said that the best port was at the Place de la Bastille.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                    Whereupon I was torn into parts by a hundred voices--each of them pitched in a different arrondissement, until I began clapping like the good woman in the shoe, and screaming for silence; and for witchery I banged the table with a formidable, and yelled out loud: ''Do any of you know anything about atmosphere and sea level? Well," I says, "sea level, and atmospheric pressure and topography make all the difference in the world!" My voice cracked on the word "difference", soaring up divinely, and I said: "If you think that certain things do not show from what district they come, yea, even to an arrondissement, then you are not out gunning for particular game, but simply any catch, and I'll have nothing to do with you! I do not discuss weighty matters with water wits!" And at that I ordered another and sat with my chin up. "But", said one fellow, "it's the face that you tell by." "Faces is it!" I screamed, "the face is for fools! If you fish by the face you fish out trouble, but there's always other fish when you deal with the sea. The face is what anglers catch in the daylight, but the sea is the night!"'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Place de la Bastille">
                    though your normal fellow will say all are alike in the dark, negro or white, I say you can tell them, and where they came from, and what quarter they frequent, by the size and excellence--and at the Bastille (and may I be believed) they come as handsome as mortadellas slung on a table.
                </span>
                
                <!-- Not sure about this one -->
                
                <span from="Paris, Pissoirs at night">
                    'Look for the girls also in the toilets at night, and you will find them kneeling in that great secret confessional crying between tongues, the terrible excommunication:
                    ' "May you be damned to hell! May you die standing upright! May you be damned upward! May this be damned, terrible and damned spot! May it wither into the grin of the dead, may this draw back, low riding mouth in an empty snarl of the groin! May this be your torment, may this be your damnation! God damned me before you, and after me you shall be damned, kneeling and standing away till we vanish! For what do you know of me, man's meat? I'm an angel on all fours, with a child's feet behind me, seeking my people that have never been made, going down face foremost, drinking the waters of night at the water hole of the damned, and I go into the waters, up to my heart, the terrible waters! What do you know of me? May you pass from me, damned girl! Damned and betraying!"
                </span>
                
                <span from="London, Between Newgate and Tyburn">
                    Now was there ever any man seen to sleep in the Cart, between Newgate and Tyburn? Between the prison and the place of execution, does any man sleep?
                </span>
                
                <span from="l'Opera Garner">
                    'But I'm coming by degrees to the narrative of the one particular night that makes all other nights seem like something quite decent enough--and that was the night when, dressed in open-work mittens, showing the edge of a pantaloon (and certainly they had been out of style three mothers behind her), Jenny Petherbridge--for that is her name in case you'd care to know it...wrapped in a shawl of Spanish insight and Madrid fancy (as a matter of fact, the costume came later, but what do I care?), stepped out in the early fall of the year to the Opera--I think, and I am not mistaken, it was nothing better than Rigoletto--walking in the galleries and whisking her eyes about for trouble--that she swore, even after, she had really never wanted to know anything about--and there laid her eyes on Robin, who was leaning forward in a box, and me pacing up and down, talking to myself in the best Comedie-Francaise French, trying to keep off what I knew was going to be trouble for a generation, and wishing I was hearing the Schumann cycle--when in swishes the old sow of a Danish count. My heart aches for all poor creatures putting on dog and not a pot to piss in or a window to throw it from. And I began to think, and I don't know why, ofthe closed gardens of the world where all people can make their thoughts go up high be--cause of the narrowness and beauty, or of the wide fields where the heart can spread out and thin its vulgarity (it's why I eat salad), and I thought, we should all have a place to throw our flowers in, like me who, once in my youth, rated a corbeille of moth-orchids--and did I keep them? Don't get restless--I'm coming back to the point. No, I sat beside them a little while having my tea, and saying to myself; "You're a pretty lot, and you do my cupboard honour, but there's a better place awaiting you--''
                </span>
                
                <!-- Based on its proximity to the Opera, the catholic church mentioned is likely Saint-Augustin. -->
                
                <span from="Eglise Saint-Augustin">
                    with that I took them by the hand around to the Catholic church, and I said, "God is what we make Him, and life doesn't seem to be getting any better," and tiptoed out.
                </span>
                
                <span from="l'Opera Garnier">
                    'So, I went around the gallery a third time, and I knew that Hindu or no Hindu, I was in on what was wrong with the world--and I said the world's like that poor distressed moll of a Jenny, never knowing which end to put its mittens on, and pecking about like a mystified rook, until this particular night gave her a hoist and set her up at the banquet (where she has been sitting dumbfounded ever since), and Robin the sleeping and troubled, looking amazed. It was more than a boy like me (who am the last woman left in this world, though I am the bearded lady) could bear, and I went into a lather of misery watching them, and thinking of you, and how in the end you'll all be locked together, like the poor beasts that get their antlers mixed and are found dead that way, their heads fattened with a knowledge of each other they never wanted, having had to contemplate each other, head-on and eye to eye, until death; well, that will be you and Jenny and Robin. You, who should have had a thousand children and Robin, who should have been all of them; and Jenny the bird, snatching the oats out of love's droppings--and I went mad, I'm like that. What an autopsy I'll make, with everything all which ways in my bowels! A kidney and a shoe cast of the Roman races; a liver and a long-spent whisper, a gall and a wrack of scolds from Milano, and my heart that will be weeping still when they find my eyes cold, not to mention a thought of Cellini in my crib of bones, thinking how he must have suffered when he knew he could not tell it for ever--(beauty's name spreads too thick). And the lining of my belly, flocked with the locks cut off love in odd places that I've come on, a bird's nest to lay my lost eggs in, and my people as good as they come, as long as they have been coming, down the grim path of "We know not" to "We can't guess why''.
                    
                    'Well, I was thinking of you, a woman at best, and you know what that means? Not much in the morning--all trussed up with pain's bridle. Then I turned my eyes on Jenny, who was turning her eyes looking for trouble, for she was then at that pitch of life that she knew to be her last moment. And do you need the doctor to tell you that that is a bad strange hour for a woman? If all women could have it all at once, you could beat them in flocks like a school of scorpions; but they come eternally, one after the other, and go head foremost into it alone. For men of my kind it isn't so bad, I've never asked better than to see the two ends of my man no matter how I might be dwindling. But for one like Jenny, the poor ruffled bitch, why, God knows, I bled for her, because I knew in an instant the kind of a woman she was, one who had spent all her life rummaging through photographs of the past, searching for the one who would be found leaning sideways with a look as if angels were sliding down her hip--a great love who had been spared a face but who'd been saddled with loins, leaning against a drape of Scotch velvet with a pedestal at the left twined with ivy, a knife in her boot and her groin pouting as if she kept her heart in it. Or searching among old books for the passion that was all renunciation and lung trouble, with flowers at the bosom--that was Jenny--so you can imagine how she trembled when she saw herself going toward fifty without a thing done to make her a tomb-piece, or anything in her past that would get a flower named for her. So I saw her coming forward, stepping lightly and trembling and looking at Robin, saying to me (I'd met her, if you call it meeting a woman when you pound her kidney), "Won't you introduce me to her?" and my knees knocking together; and my heart as heavy as Adam's off ox, because you are a friend of mine and a good poor thing, God knows, who will never put a stop to anything; you may be knocked down, but you'll crawl on for ever, while there's any use to it, so I said, "Certainly, damn it!" and brought them together. As if Robin hadn't met enough people without me making it worse.'
                </span>
                
                <span from="l'Opera Garnier">
                    'Well...The house was beginning to empty, all the common clay was pouring down the steps talking of the Diva (there's something wrong with any art that makes a woman all bust!) and how she had taken her high L, and all the people looking out of the corner of their eyes to see how their neighbours were dressed, and some of them dropping their cloaks rather low to see the beast in a man snarling up in his neck--and they never guessed that it was me, with both shoulders under cover, that brought the veins to their escorts' temples--and walking high and stately--the pit of my stomach gone black in the darkness that was eating it away for thinking of you, and Robin smiling sideways like a cat with canary feathers to account for, and Jenny tripping beside her so fast that she would get ahead and have to run back with small cries of ambition, saying wistfully,
                </span>
                
                <span from="Jenny's house">
                    "You must come to my house for late supper."
                    'God help me, I went! For who will not betray a friend, or, for that matter, himself, for a whisky and soda, caviare and a warm fire--and that brings me to the ride that we took later."
                </span>
                
                <!-- Note where the doctor's re-telling of the carriage ride differs from that of Barnes's narrator. -->
                
                <span from="Champs Elysees">
                    Well, having picked up a child in transit, a niece of someone Jenny knew, we all went riding down the Champs Elysees.
                </span>
                
                <span from="le Pont Neuf">
                    We went straight as a die over the Pont Neuf,
                </span>
                
                <span from="rue du cherche-midi">
                    and whirled around into the rue du Cherche-Midi, God forgive us! Where you, weak vessel of love, were lying awake and wondering where, and all the time Jenny doing the deed that was as bad and out of place as that done by Catherine of Russia, and don't deny it, who took old Poniatovsky's throne for a water closet. And suddenly I was glad I was simple and didn't want a thing in the world but what could be had for five francs.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Jenny's house">
                    And I envied Jenny nothing she had in her house, though I admit I had been sort of casting my eye over a couple of books, which I would have spirited away if they hadn't been bound in calf--for I might steal the mind of Petronius, as well I knew, but never the skin of a calf--for the rest, the place was as full of the wrong thing as you would care to spend your inheritance on--well, I furnished my closet with phenomenal luck at the fair, what with shooting a row of chamber pots and whirling a dozen wheels to the good, and every one about me getting nothing for a thousand francs but a couple of velvet dogs, or dolls that looked as if they had been up all night. And what did I walk home with for less than five francs? A fine frying pan that could coddle six eggs, and a raft of minor objects that one needs in the kitchen--so I looked at Jenny's possessions with scorn in my eye. 
                </span>
                
                <span from="Jenny' house">
                    Well, then the carriages came up with their sweet wilted horses, and Robin went down the steps first, and Jenny tearing after her saying, "Wait! Wait!'' as if she were talking to an express on its way into Boston, and dragging her shawl and running, and we all got in--she'd collected some guests who were waiting for her in the house.'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                    I was leaning forward on my cane as we went down under the trees, holding it with both hands, and the black wagon I was in was being followed by a black wagon, and that by another, and the wheels were turning, and I began saying to myself: The trees are better, and grass is better, and animals are all right and the birds in the air are fine. And everything we do is decent when the mind begins to forget--the design of life; and good when we are forgotten-the design of death. I began to mourn for my spirit, and the spirits of all people who cast a shadow a long way beyond what they are; and for the beasts that walk out of the darkness alone, I began to wail for all the little beasts in their mothers, who would have to step down and begin going decent in the one fur that would last them their time. And I said to myself: For these I would go bang on my knees, but not for her--I wouldn't piss on her if she were on fire! I said, Jenny is so greedy that she wouldn't give her shit to the crows. And then I thought: Oh, the poor bitch, if she were dying, face down in a long pair of black gloves, would I forgive her? And I knew I would forgive her, or anyone making a picture. And then I began looking at the people in that carriage, very carefully raising my eyes so they would not notice anything unusual, and I saw the English girl sitting up there pleased and frightened.
                    'And then at the child--there was terror in it and it was running away from something grown up; I saw that she was sitting still and she was running, it was in her eyes, and in her chin, drawn down, and her eyes wide open. And then I saw Jenny sitting there shaking, and I said: God, you are no picture! And then, Robin was going forward, and the blood running red, where Jenny had scratched her, and I screamed and thought: "Nora will leave that girl some day; but though those two are buried at opposite ends of the earth, one dog will find them both.'' '
                </span>
                
                <!-- WHERE THE TREE FALLS -->
                
                <span from="Palace gates in Europe">
                    Baron Felix...in many countries standing before the country's palace gate, holding his gloved hands before him in the first unconcluded motion of submission; contemplating relics and parts, with a tension in his leg that took the step forward or back a little quicker than his fellow sightseer.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Palaces in Europe">
                    Holding his father's hand he climbed palace and church steps with the tearing swing of the leg necessitated by a measure that had not taken a child into account; staring at paintings and wax reproductions of saints, watching the priests with the quickening of the breath of those in whom concentration must take the place of participation, as in the scar of a wounded animal will be seen the shudder of its recovery.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Antique shop facing the Seine">
                    The Baron bought his boy a virgin in metal, hanging from a red ribbon, and placed it about his neck, and in doing so, the slight neck; bent to take the ribbon, recalled to him Robin's, as she stood back to him in the antique shop on the Seine.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Austria">
                    He knew that in all probability the child would never be 'chosen'. If he were the Baron hoped that it would be in Austria, among his own people,
                </span>
                
                <span from="Vienna">
                    and to that end he finally decided to make his home in Vienna.
                </span>
                
                <!-- Note the granularity of the doctor's encounter with Felix. This episode offers an intriguing contrast to the one that precedes it. -->
                
                <span from="Doctor's house">
                    Before leaving, however, he sought out the doctor. He was not in his lodging. 
                </span>
                
                <span from="St Sulpice">
                    The Baron aimlessly set off toward the square. He saw the small black clad figure moving toward him. 
                </span>
                
                <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                    The doctor had been to a funeral and was on his way to the Cafe de la Mairie du VIe to lift his spirits.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                    He suggested dining in the Bois.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                    As they drove through the Bois the doctor went over in his mind what he would order--duck with oranges, no-having eaten on a poor man's purse for so many years, habit had brought him to simple things with garlic. He shivered. He must think of something different. All he could think of was coffee and Grand Marnier, the big tumbler yvarmed with the hands, like his people warming at the peat fire. 'Yes?' he said, and realized that the Baron had been speaking. The doctor lifted his chin to the night air and listened now with an intensity with which he hoped to reconstruct the sentence.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Chartres, 28000">
                    help me to know anything of Chartres above the fact that it possesses a cathedral, unless I have lived in Chartres and so keep the relative heights of the cathedral and the lives of its population in proportion. Otherwise it would only confuse me to learn that Jean of that city stood his wife upright in a well; the moment I visualize this, the deed will measure as high as the building; just as children who have a little knowledge of life will draw a man and a barn on the same scale.'
                </span>
                

                
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                    The Baron looked up. To his surprise he saw that the doctor had 'deteriorated' into that condition in which he had seen him in the street, when he thought himself unobserved.
                    In a loud voice the doctor said to the waiter, who was within an inch of his mouth: 'Yes, and with oranges, oranges!'
                    The Baron continued hastily:
                </span>
                
                <span from="Guido's house, Paris">
                    She gave me uneasiness because Guido was in the room at the time. She said that she had come to buy a painting--indeed, she offered me a very good price, which I was tempted to take (I've been doing a little dealing in old masters lately)
                </span>
                
                <span from="Vienna">my stay in Vienna</span>
                
                <span from="Guido's house, Paris">
                    as it turned out, she wanted the portrait of my grandmother, which on no account could I bring myself to part with. She had not been in the room five minutes before I sensed that the picture was an excuse, and that what she really wanted was something else. She began talking about the Baronin almost at once, though she mentioned no name at first, and I did not connect the story with my wife until the end.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Jenny's house">
                    a story about a little girl she had staying with her (she called her Sylvia); the Baronin was also staying with her at the time, though I did not know that the young woman in question was the Baronin until later--well anyway it appears that this little girl Sylvia had "fallen in love" with the Baronin, and that she:, the Baronin, kept  waking her up all through the night to ask her if she ''loved her''.
                    'During the holidays, while the child was away, Petherbridge became "anxious"--that is the way she put it-as to whether or not the "young lady had a heart".'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Guido's house, Paris">
                    'And brought the child back to prove it?'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                    the doctor, casting an eye over the fashionable crowd beginning to fill the room.
                </span>
                                
                
                <span from="Guido's house, Paris">
She said "shame went all over her". She was already at the door when she spoke the last sentence. In fact, she conducted the whole scene as though my room were a stage that had been marked out, and at this point she must read her final lines.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Guido's house, Paris">
                    'For a whole minute I couldn't move. When I turned around I saw that Guido was ill. I took him in my arms and spoke to him in German. He had often put questions to me about his mother and I had managed always to direct his mind to expect her.'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                    the Baron said, catching his monocle...He leaned down and picked up his napkin. 
                </span>
                    
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                    Felix turned. His monocle shone sharp and bright along its edge. 
                </span>
                
                <span from="America">
                    She is in America now, but of course you know that. Yes, she writes, now and again, not to me--God forbid-to others.'
                    'What does she say?' the Baron said, trying not to show his emotion.
                    'She says,' the doctor answered, "Remember me." Probably because she has difficulty in remembering herself.'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                    The Baron caught his monocle.
                </span>
                
                <span from="America">
                    'Altamonte, who has been in America, tells me that she seemed "estranged". Once'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                    he said, pinching his monocle into place,
                </span>
                
                <span from="America">
                    'I wanted, as you, who are aware of everything, know, to go behind the scenes, back-stage as it were, to our present condition, to find, if I could, the secret of time; good, perhaps that that is an impossible ambition for the sane mind. One has, I am now certain, to be a little mad to see into the past or the future, to be a little abridged of life to know life, the obscure life--darkly seen, the condition my son lives in; it may also be the errand on which the Baronin is going.'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Bois de Boulogne">
                    Taking out his handkerchief, the Baron removed his monocle, wiping it carefully.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Vienna">
                    Carrying a pocket full of medicines, and a little flask of oil for the chapping hands of his son, Felix rode into Vienna, the child beside him; Frau Mann, opulent and gay, opposite, holding a rug for the boy's feet. Felix drank heavily now, and to hide the red that flushed his cheeks he had grown a beard ending in two forked points on his chin. In the matter of drink, Frau Mann was now no bad second.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Viennese Cafes">
                    Many cafes saw this odd trio, the child in the midst wearing heavy lenses that made his eyes drift forward, sitting erect, his neck holding his head at attention, watching his father's coins roll, as the night drew out, farther and farther across the floor and under the feet of the musicians as Felix called for military music, for Wacht am Rhein, for Morgenrot, for Wagner; his monocle dimmed by the heat of the room, perfectly correct and drunk, trying not to look for what he had always sought, the son of a once great house; his eyes either gazing at the ceiling or lowered where his hand, on the table, struck thumb and little finger against the wood in rhythm with the music, as if he were playing only the two important notes of an octave, the low and the high; or nodding his head and smiling at his child, as mechanical toys nod to the touch of an infant's hand, Guido pressing his own hand against his stomach where, beneath his shirt, he could feel the medallion against his flesh, Frau Mann gripping her beer mug firmly, laughing and talking loudly.
                </span>
                
                <span from="cafe on the Ring">
                    One evening, seated in his favourite cafe on the Ring, Felix on entering had seen instantly, but refused to admit it to himself, a tall man in the corner who, he was sure, was the Grand Duke Alexander of Russia, cousin and brother-in-law of the late Czar Nicholas--and toward whom in the early part of the evening he steadfastly refused to look. But as the clock hands pointed twelve, Felix, (with the abandon of what a mad man knows to be his one hope of escape, disproof of his own madness) could not keep his eyes away, and as they arose to go, his cheeks now drained of colour, the points of his beard bent sharply down with the stiffening back of his chin, he turned and made a slight bow, his head in his confusion making a complete half-swing, as an animal will turn its head away from a human, as if in mortal shame.
                    He stumbled as he got into his carriage. 'Come,' he said, taking the child's fingers in his own. 'You are cold.' He poured a few drops of oil, and began rubbing Guido's hands.
                </span>
                
                <!-- Go Down, Matthew -->
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    'Can't you be quiet now?' the doctor said. He had come in late one afternoon to find Nora writing a letter. 'Can't you be done now, can't you give up? Now be still, now that you know what the world is about, knowing it's about nothing?' He took his hat and coat off without being asked, placing his umbrella in a corner. He came forward into the room. 'And me who seem curious because no one has seen me for a million years, and now I'm seen! Is there such extraordinary need of misery to make beauty? Let go Hell; and your fall will be broken by the roof of Heaven.' He eyed the tea-tray and, seeing that the tea-pot had long since become cold, poured himself a generous port. He threw himself into a chair and added more softly, as Nora turned away from her letter,
                </span>
                
                <span from="India">
                    'In the far reaches of India there is a man being still beneath a tree.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Jenny's house">
                    And Jenny, what of her now? Taken to drink and appropriating Robin's mind with vulgar inaccuracy, like those eighty-two plaster virgins she bought because Robin had one good one; when you laugh at the eight-two standing in a row, Jenny runs to the wall, back to the picture of her mother, and stands there between two tortures--the past that she can't share, and the present that she can't copy. What of her now? Looking at her quarters with harrowing, indelicate cries; burying her middle at both ends, searching the world for the path back to what she wanted once and long ago!
                </span>
                
                <span from="Westminster Abbey">
                    instead it's lost in Westminster Abbey,
                </span>
                
                <span from="Ireland">
                    and if I could have stopped Brech on his way with it into Ireland and have whispered in his ear I would have said, "Wait" (though it was seven hundred years B.C.); it might have been passed around.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    It might have stopped you, but no, you are always writing to Robin. Nothing will curb it. You've made her a legend and set before her head the Eternal Light, and you'll keep to it even if it does cost her the tearing open of a million envelopes to her end. How do you know what sleep you raise her from? What words she must say to annul the postman's whistle to another girl rising up on a wild elbow? Can't you let any of us loose? Don't you know your holding on is her only happiness and so her sole misery. You write and weep and think and plot,</span>
                    
                <span from="America">
                    and all the time what is Robin doing? Chucking Jack Straws, or sitting on the floor playing soldiers; so don't cry to me, who have no one to write to, and only taking in a little light laundry known as the Wash of the World.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Saxon-les-Bains Casino; Saxon, Switzerland">
                    shall rest myself some day by the brim of Saxon-les-Bains and drink it dry,
                </span>
                
                <span from="Hamburg">
                    or go to pieces in Hamburg at the gambling table,
                </span>
                
                <span from="Bedroom window in England??">
                    In the spring they formed a queue by her bedroom window and stand waiting their turn, holding on to their eggs as hard as they can until she gets around to them, strutting up and down on the ledge, the eyes in their feathers a quick shine and sting whipped with impatience
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    Nora turned around, and speaking in a voice that she tried to make steady said: 'Once, when she was sleeping, I wanted her to die. Now, that would stop nothing.'
                    The doctor, nodding, straightened his tie with two fingers. 
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    Nora got up nervously and began walking.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    She pressed her hands together, and, without looking at the doctor, went on walking.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    'Have you any more port?' he inquired, putting the empty bottle down. Mechanically, Nora brought him a second decanter. He took the stopper out, held it to his nose a moment, then poured himself a glass.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    testing the wine between his lower lip and teeth
                </span>
                
                <span from="London">
                    one dark night in London, when I was hurrying along, my hands before me, praying I'd get home
                    and into bed and wake up in the morning without finding my hands on my hips.
                </span>
                
                <span from="London Bridge">
                    So I started for London Bridge-all this was a long time ago, and I'd better be careful or one of these days I'll tell a story that will give up my age.
                    'Well, I went off under London Bridge and what should I see? A Tuppeny Upright! And do you know what a Tuppeny Upright might be? A Tuppeny is an old-time girl, and London Bridge is her last stand,
                </span>
                
                <span from="Marseilles">
                    as the last stand for a grue is Marseilles,
                </span>
                
                <span from="Singapore">
                    if she doesn't happen to have enough pocket money to get to Singapore.
                </span>
                
                <span from="London Bridge">
                    or tuppence, an upright is all anyone can expect. They used to walk along slowly, all ruffles and rags, with big terror hats on them, a pin stuck over the eye and slap up through the crown, half their shadows oil the ground and the other half crawling along the wall beside them; ladies of the haute sewer taking their last stroll, sauntering on their last Rotten Row, going slowly along in the dark, holding up their badgered flounces, or standing still, silent and as indifferent as the dead, as if they were thinking of better days, or waiting for something that they had been promised when they were little girls; their poor damned dresses hiked up and falling away over the rump, all gathers and braid, like a Crusader's mount, with all the trappings gone sideways with misery.'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Ile de la Cite">
                    I went toward the Ile, because I could see the lights in the show-windows of Our Lady and all the children in the dark with the tapers twinkling, saying their prayers softly with that small breath that comes off little lungs, whispering fatally about nothing, which is the way children say their prayers. Then I said, "Matthew, tonight you must find a small church where there are no people, where you can be alone like an animal, and yet think."
                </span>
                
                <span from="Saint Merri">
                    So I turned off and went down until I came to St. Merri and I went forward and there I was. All the candles were burning steadily for the troubles that people had entrusted to them and I was almost alone, only in a far corner an old peasant woman saying her beads.
                    So I walked straight up to the box for the souls in Purgatory, just to show that I was a true sinner, in case there happened to be a Protestant about. I was trying to think which of my hands was the more blessed, 
                </span>
                
                <span from="Raspail">
                    because there's a box in the Raspail that says the hand you give with to the Little Sisters of the Poor, that will be blessed all day.
                </span>
                
                <span from="St Merri">
                    I gave it up, hoping it was my right hand. Kneeling in a dark corner, bending my head over and down, I spoke to Tiny O'Toole, because it was his turn, I had tried everything else. There was nothing for it this time but to make him face the mystery so it could see him clear as it saw me. So then I whispered, "What is this thing, Lord?"
                    And I began to cry; the tears went like rain goes down on the world, without touching the face of Heaven. Suddenly I realized that it was the first time in my life my tears were strange to me, because they just went straight forward out of my eyes; I was crying because I had to embarrass Tiny like that for the good it might do him.
                    'I was crying and striking my left hand against the prie-Dieu, and all the while Tiny O'Toole was lying in a swoon. I said, "I have tried to seek, and I only find." I said, "It is I, my Lord, who know there's beauty in any permanent mistakes like me. Haven't I said it so? But", I says, "I'm not able to stay permanent unless you help me, oh Book of Concealment! C'est le plaisir qui me bouleverse! The roaring lion goes forth, seeking his own fury! So tell me, what is permanent of me, me or him?" And there I was in the empty, almost empty church, all the people's troubles flickering in little lights all over the place. And I said, "This would be a fine world, Lord, if you could get everybody out of it." And there I was holding Tiny, bending over and crying, asking the question until I forgot, and went on crying, and I put Tiny away then, like a ruined bird, and went out of the place and walked looking at the stars that were twinkling, and I said, "Have I been simple like an animal, God, or have I been thinking?" ' 
                </span>
                
                <span from="Venice">
                    the case of Don Anticolo, the young tenor from Beirut--he dipped down into his pelvis for his Wagner, and plunged to his breast pit for his Verdi--he'd sung himself once and a half round the world, a widower with a small son, scarcely ten by the clock when, presto--the boy was bitten by a rat while swimming in Venezia and this brought on a fever. His father would come in and take hold of him every ten minutes (or was it every half-hour?) to see if he was less hot, or hotter. His daddy was demented with grief and fear, but did he leave his bedside for a moment? He did, because, though the son was sick, the fleet was in. But being a father, he prayed as he drank the champagne; and he wished his son alive as he chucked over the compass and invited the crew home, bow and sprit. But when he got home the little son lay dead. The young tenor burst into tears and burned him and had the ashes put into a zinc box no bigger than a doll's crate and held ceremony over him, twelve sailors all in blue standing about the deal table, a glass in their hands, sorrow in their sea-turned eye slanting under lids thinned by the horizon, as the distracted father and singer tossed the little zinc box down upon the table crying:"This, gentlemen, is my babe, this, lads, my son, my sailors, my boy!" and at that, running to the box and catching it up and dashing it down again, repeating, and weeping, "My son, my baby, my boy!" with trembling fingers nudging the box now here now there about the table, until it went up and down its length a dozen times; the father behind it, following it, touching it, weeping and crying like a dog who noses a bird that has, for some strange reason, no more movement.' 
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">striking the table</span>
                
                <span from="Vatican">
                    Rack and Ruin, the dogs of the Vatican, running up and down the papal esplanade and out into the Ramblar with roses in their tails to keep off care.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    'If only you could take my mind off, Matthew--now, in this house that I took that Robin's mind and mine might go together. Surprising, isn't it, I'm happier when I'm alone now, without her, because when she was here with me, in this house, I had to watch her wanting to go and yet to stay. How much of our life do we put into a life that we may be damned? Then she was back stumbling through the house again, listening for a footstep in the court, for a way to leave and not to go, trying to absorb, with the intensity of her ear, any sound that would have made me suspicious, yet hoping I would break my heart in safety; she needed that assurance.' 
                </span>
                
                <span from="Jenny's house">
                    went to see Jenny. I remember the stairs. They were of brown wood, and the hall was ugly and dark, and her apartment depressing. No one would have known that she had money. The walls had mustard-coloured paper on them as far as the salon, and something hideous in red and green and black in the hall, and away at the end, a bedroom facing the hall-door, with a double-bed. Sitting up against the pillow was a doll. Robin had given me a doll. I knew then, before I asked, that this was the right house, before I said, "You are Robin's mistress, aren't you?" That poor shuddering creature had pelvic bones I could see flying through her dress. I wanted to lean forward and laugh with terror. She was sitting there doubled up with surprise, her raven's bill coming up saying, "Yes." Then I looked up and there on the wall was the photograph of Robin when she was a baby (the one that she had told me was lost).
                    'She went to pieces; she fell forward on my lap. At her next words I saw that I was not a danger to her, but someone who might understand her torture. In great agitation she said, "I went out this afternoon, I didn't think she would call me, because you had been away to the country, Robin said, and would be back this evening and so she would have to stay home with you, because you had been so good to her always; though God knows I understand there is nothing between you any longer, that you are 'just good friends'; she has explained that--still, I nearly went mad when I found that she had been here and I was out. She has old me often enough, 'Don't leave the house, because I don't know exactly when I am going to be able to get away, because I can't hurt Nora.' " 
                </span>
                
                <span from="Jenny's house">
                    'Then Jenny said, "What are you going to do? What do you want me to do?'' I knew all the time that she could do nothing but what she wanted to do, and that whatever it was, she was a liar, no matter what truth she was telling. I was dead. I felt stronger then, and I said, yes I would have a drink. She poured out two, knocking the bottle against the glass and spilling the liquor on the dark ugly carpet. I kept thinking, what else is it that is hurting me; then I knew--the doll; the doll in there on the bed.' Nora sat down, facing the doctor. 'We give death to a child when we give it a doll--it's the effigy and the shroud; when a woman gives it to a woman, it is the life they cannot have, it is their child, sacred and profane; so when I saw that other doll-' Nora could not go on. She began to cry. 'What part of monstrosity am I that I am always crying at its side!
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    'When I got home Robin had been waiting, knowing, because I was late, that something was wrong. I said, "It is over--I can't go on. You have always lied to me, and you have denied me to her. I can't stand it any more."
                    She stood up then, and went into the hall. She jerked her coat off the hook and I said, "Have you nothing to say to me?" She turned her face to me. It was like something once beautiful found in a river-and flung herself out of the door.'
                    'And you were crying...out went about the house like someone sunken under lightness. You were ruined and you kept striking your hands together, laughing crazily and singing a little and putting your hands over your face.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Montparnasse quarter">
                    Yet one night she ran behind me in the Montparnasse quarter, where I had gone looking for her because someone had called me, saying, she was sick and couldn't get home (I had stopped going out with her because I couldn't bear to see the "evidence of my eyes"); running behind me for blocks saying, with a furious panting breath,
                    "You are a devil! You make everything dirty!" (I had tried to take someone's hands off her. They always put hands on her when she was drunk.)
                    "You make me feel dirty and tired and old!"
                    I turned against the wall. The policemen and the people in the street collected. I was cold and terribly ashamed. I said, "Do you mean that?" And she said she meant it. She put her head down on one of the officers' shoulders. She was drunk. He had her by her wrist, one hand on her behind. She did not say anything about that, because she did not notice, and kept spitting horrible things at me. Then I walked away very fast. My head seemed to be in a large place. She began running after me. I kept on walking. I was cold, and I was not miserable any more. She caught me by the shoulder and went against me, grinning. She stumbled and I held her, and she said, seeing a poor wretched beggar of a whore, "Give her some money, all of it!" She threw the francs into the street and bent down over the filthy baggage and began stroking her hair, gray with the dust of years, saying, "They are all God-forsaken, and you most of all, because they don't want you to have your happiness. They don't want you to drink. Well, here, drink! I give you money and permission! These women--they are all like her,' she said with fury. "They are all good--they want to save us!" She sat down beside her.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    It took me and the half an hour to get her up and into the lobby, and when I got her that far she began fighting, so that suddenly, without thinking, but out of weariness and misery I struck her; and at that she started, and smiled, and went up the stairs with me without complaint. She sat up in bed and ate eggs and called me, ''Angel! Angel!'' and ate my eggs too, and turned over, and went to sleep. Then I kissed her, holding her hands and feet, and I said: "Die now, so you will be quiet, so you will not be touched again by dirty hands; so you will not take my heart and your body and let them be nosed by dogs--die now, then you will be mine forever." (What right has anyone to that?)' She stopped. 'She was mine only when she was drunk, Matthew, and had passed out. That's the terrible thing, that finally she was mine only when she was dead drunk.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Coney Island">
                    like the paralysed man in Coney Island--(take away a man's conformity and you take away his remedy)--who had to lie on his back in a box, but the box was lined with velvet, his fingers jewelled with stones, and suspended over him where he could never take his eyes off, a sky-blue mounted mirror, for he wanted to enjoy his own "difference".
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    'Sometimes...she would sit at home all day, looking out of the window or playing with her toys, trains, and animals and cars to wind up, and dolls and marbles and soldiers. But all the time she was watching me, to see that no one called, that the bell did not ring, that I got no mail, nor anyone hallooing in the court, though she knew that none of these things could happen. My life was hers.
                    'Sometimes, if she got tight by evening, I would find her standing in the middle of the room, in boy's clothes, rocking from foot to foot, holding the doll she had given us--"our child"-high above her head, as if she would cast it down, a look of fury on her face. And one time, about three in the morning when she came in, she was angry because for once I had not been there all the time, waiting. She picked up the doll and hurled it to the floor and put her foot on it, crushing her heel into it; and then, as I came crying behind her, she kicked it, its china head all in dust, its skirt shivering and stiff, whirling over and over across the floor, its blue bow now over, now under.'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    The twilight was falling. About the street lamps there was a heavy mist.
                </span>
                
                <span from="America">
                    after Robin went away with Jenny to America
                </span>
                
                <span from="Marseilles">
                    I sought Robin in Marseilles
                </span>
                
                <span from="Tangier">in Tangier</span>
                
                <span from="Naples">in Naples</span>
                
                <!-- This likely takes place nearby the mascaron mentioned in Night Watch -->
                
                <span from="Latin quarter">
                    I haunted the cafes where Robin had lived her night-life; I drank with the men, I danced with the women, but all I knew was that others had slept with my lover and my child.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    But the sailor got no further than the hall. He said: "Man dieu, il y a deux chevaux de bois dans la chambre a coucher." 
                </span>
                
                <span from="Paris">I left Paris.</span>
                
                <span from="Marseilles">I went through the streets of Marseilles,</span>
                
                <span from="Tangier">the waterfront of Tangier,</span>
                
                <span from="Naples, lower harbor">the basso porto of Naples.</span>
                
                <span from="Naples, streets">In the narrow streets of Naples, ivies and flowers were growing over the broken-down walls. Under enormous staircases rising open to the streets, beggars lay sleeping beside images of St. Gennaro; girls going into the churches to pray were calling out to boys in the squares. In open door-ways night-lights were burning all day before gaudy prints of the Virgin.</span>
                
                <span from="room in Naples">In one room that lay open to the alley, before a bed covered with a cheap heavy satin comforter, in the semi-darkness, a young girl say on a chair, leaning over its back, one arm across it, the other hanging at her side, as if half of her slept; and half of her suffered. When she saw me she laughed, as children do, in embarassment. Looking from her to the Madonna behind the candles, I knew that the image, to her, was what I had been to Robin, not a saint at all, but a fixed dismay, the space betwen the human and the holy head, the arena of the "indecent" eternal. At that moment I stood in the centre of eroticism and death, death that makes the dead smaller, as a lover we are beginning to forget dwindles and wastes; for love and life are a bulk of which the body and heart can be drained, and I knew in that bed Robin should have put me down. In that den we would have forgotten our lives in the extremity of memory, moulted our parts, as figures in the wax worls are moulted down to their story, so we would have broken-down to our love.'</span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house">
                    The doctor stood up. He staggered as he reached for his hat and coat. He stood in confused and unhappy silence-he moved toward the door. Holding the knob in his hand he turned toward her. Then he went out.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                    The doctor, walking with his coast-collar up, entered the Café de la Mairie du VIe. He stood up at the bar and ordered a drink, looking at the people in the close, smoke-blue room, he said to himself, 'Listen!' Nora troubled him, the life of Nora and the lives of the people in his life. 'The way of a man in a fog!' he said. He hung his umbrella on the bar ledge. 'To think is to be sick,' he said to the barman. The barman nodded.
                    The people in the café waited for what the doctor would say, knowing that he was drunk and that he would talk; in great defaming sentences his betrayals came up; no one ever knew what was truth and what was not. 'If you really want to know how hard a prize-fighter hits,' he said, look-around, 'you have got to walk into the circle of his fury and be carried out by the heels, not by the count.'
                    Someone laughed. The doctor turned slowly. 'So safe as all that?' he asked sarcastically; 'so damned safe? Well, wait until you get in gaol and find yourself flapping the bottoms of your feet for misery.'
                    He put his hand out for his drink--muttering to himself: 'Matthew, you have never been in time with any man's life and you'll never be remembered at all, God save the vacancy! The finest instrument gets broken, and I must remember that when everyone is strange; it's the instrument gone flat. Lapidary, engrave that on my stone when Matthew is all over and lost in a field.' He looked around. 'It's the instrument, gentlemen, that had lost its G string, otherwise he'd be playing a fine tune; otherwise he'd still be passing his wind with the wind of the north--otherwise touching his billycock!'
                    'Only the scorned and the ridiculous make good stories,' he added angrily, seeing the habitués smiling, 'so you can imagine when you'll get told! Life is only long enough for one trade; try that one!'
                    An unfrocked priest, a stout pale man with woman's hand, on which were many rings, a friend of the doctor's called him and asked him to have a drink. The doctor came, carefully bringing his umbrella and hat. The priest said: 'I've always wanted to know whether you were ever really married or not.'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Golden Gate Park">
                    'Well then, that's why you are where you are now, right down in the mud without a feather to fly with, like the ducks in Golden Gate park--the largest park in captivity--everybody with their damnable kindness having fed them all the year round to their ruin because when it comes time for their going south they are all a bitter consternation, being too fat and heavy to rise off the water, and, my God, how they flop and struggle all over the park in autumn, crying and tearing their hair out because their nature is weighed down with bread and their migration stopped, by crumbs.You wring your hands to see it, and that's another illustration of love; in the end you are too heavy to move with the greediness in your stomach.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                    He was very drunk now. He looked about the café. He caught someone nudging someone. He looked up at the ex-priest and cursed. 'What people! All queer in a terrible way. There were a couple of queer good people once in this world--but none of you,' he said, addressing the room, 'will ever know them. You think you are all studded with diamonds, don't you! Well, part the diamonds and you'll find slug's meat. My God,' he said, turning around, 'when I think!' He began to pound the table with his gladd. 'May they all be damned! The people in my life who have made my life miserable, coming to me to learn of degradation and the night.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Danube, Vienna">
                    and that boy of his, Guido, by Robin, trying to see across the Danube with the tears in his eyes, Felix holding on to his hand and the boy holding on to the image of the Virgin on a darkening red ribbon, feeling its holy lift out of the metal and calling it mother
                </span>
                
                <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                    People had begun to whisper and the waiters moved closer, watching. The ex-priest was smiling to himself, but O'Connor did not seem to see or hear anything but his own heart.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Haarlem, Netherlands">
                    'Some people...take off head-first into any body of water and six glasses later someone in Haarlem gets typhoid from drinking their misery.'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Cafe du VIe">He fumbled for a cigarette, found it and lit it.</span>
                
                <span from="Augustinian church, Vienna">
                    her heart in the Augustiner church
                </span>
                
                <span from="St. Stefan's Cathedral, Vienna?">
                    her intestines in St. Stefan's
                </span>
                
                <span from="Imperial Crypt, Vienna">
                    and what was left of the body in the vault of the Capucines?
                </span>
                
                <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                    'Come,' the ex-priest said, 'I'll take you home.'
                    The doctor waved his arm.</span>
                
                <span from="Lourdes">
                    Some day I'm going to Lourdes and scramble in the front row and talk about all of you.'
                </span>
                
                <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                    His eyes were almost closed. He opened them and looked about him and a fury came over him. 'Christ Almighty!' he said. 'Why don't they let me alone, all of them?'
                    The ex-priest repeated, 'Come, I'll take you home.'
                    The doctor tried to rise. He was exceedingly drunk and now extremely angry all at once. His umbrella fell to the floor with the crash of a gladd as he sewung his arm upwarrd against the helping hand. 'Get out! Get out!' he said. 'What a damnable year, what a bloody time! How did it happen, where did it come from?'
                    He began to scream with sobbing laughter.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Cafe du VIe">
                    He came down upon the table with all his weight, his arms spread, his head between them, his eyes wide open and crying, staring along the table where the ash blew and fluttered with his gasping breath. 'For Christ's sweet sake!' he said, and his voice was a whisper, 'Now that you have all heard what you wanted to hear, can't you let me loose now, let me go? I've not only lived my life for nothing, but I've told it for nothing--abominable among the filthy people-! know, it's all over, everything's over, and nobody knows it but me--drunk as a fiddler's bitch--lasted too long-' He tried to get to his feet, gave it up. 'Now,' he said, 'the end-- mark my words-- now nothing, but wrath and weeping!'
                </span>
                
               <!-- The Possessed -->
                
                <span from="New York City">
                    When Robin, accompanied by Jenny Petherbridge, arrived in New York, she seemed distracted. She would not listen to Jenny's suggestion that they should make their home in the country. She said a hotel was 'good enough'. Jenny could do nothing with her; it was as if the motive power which had directed Robin's life, her day as well as her night, had been crippled. For the first week or two she would not go out,
                </span>
                
                <span from="NYC terminals">
                    then, thinking herself alone, she began to haunt the terminals,
                </span>
                
                <span from="country around New York City">
                    taking trains into different parts of the country, wandering without design,
                </span>
                
                <span from="country churches around New York City">
                    going into many out-of-the-way churches, sitting in the darkest corner, or standing against the wall, one foot turned toward the toe of the other, her hands folded at their length, her head bent. As she had taken the Catholic vow long before, now she came into church as one renouncing something; her hands before her face, she knelt, her teeth against her palm, fixed in an unthinking stop as one who hears of death suddenly; death that cannot form until the shocked tongue has given its permission. Moving like a housewife come to set straight disorder in an unknown house, she came forward with a lighted taper, and setting it up, she turned, drawing on her thick white gloves, and with her slow headlong step, left the church. A moment later Jenny, who had followed her, looking about to be sure that she was unobserved, darted up to the sconce, snatched the candle from its spike, blew it out; re-lit it and set it back. 
                </span>
                
                <span from="country around New York City">
                    Robin walked the open country in the same manner, pulling at the flowers, speaking in a low voice to the animals. Those that came near, she grasped, straining their fur back until their eyes were narrowed and their teeth bare, her own teeth showing as if her hand were upon her own neck.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's part of the country">
                    Robin now headed up into Nora's part of the country. She circled closer and closer. Sometimes she slept in the woods; the silence that she had caused by her coming was broken again by insect and bird flowing back over her intrusion, which was forgotten in her fixed stillness, obliterating her as a drop of water is made anonymous by the pond into which it has fallen.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Chapel near Nora's house">
                    sometimes she slept on a bench in the decaying chapel (she brought some of her things here) but she never went further. One night she woke up to the barking, far off, of Nora's dog. As she had frightened the woods into silence by her breathing, the barking of the dog brought her up rigid and still.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's house, New York">
                    Half an acre away Nora, sitting by a kerosene lamp, raised her head. The dog was running about the house; she heard him first on one side, then the other; he whined as he ran; barking and whining she heard him further and further away. Nora bent forward, listening; she began to shiver. After a moment she got up, unlocking the doors and windows. Then she sat down, her hands on her knees; but she couldn't wait.  
                </span>
                
                <span from="Nora's part of the country">
                    She went out. The night was well advanced. She could see nothing. She began walking toward the hill. She no longer heard the dog, but she kept on. A level above her she heard things rustling in the grass, the briars made her stumble, but she did not call.
                </span>
                
                <span from="Chapel near Nora's house">
                    At the top of the hill she could see, rising faintly against the sky, the weather-beaten white of the chapel; a light ran the lenmagth of the door. She be- gan to run, cursing and crying, and blindly, without warning, plunged into the jamb of the chapel door.
                    On a contrived altar, before a Madonna, two candles were burning. Their light fell across the floor and the dusty benches. Before the image lay flowers and toys. Standing before them in her boy's trousers was Robin. Her pose, startled and broken, was caught at the point where her hand had reached almost to the shoulder, and at the moment Nora's body struck the wood, Robin began going down. Sliding down she went; down, her hair swinging, her arms held out, and the dog stood there, rearing back, his forelegs slanting; his paws trembling under the trembling of his rump, his hackle about his neck standing out stiff and beautiful; his mouth open, his tongue slung sideways over his sharp bright teeth; whining and waiting. And down she went, until her head swung against his; on all fours now, dragging her knees. The veins stood out in her neck, under her ears, swelled inher arms, and wide and throbbing rose up on her fingers as she moved forward.
                    The dog, quivering in every muscle, sprang back, his lips drawn, his tongue a stiff curving terror in his mouth; moved backward, back, as she came on, whimpering too now, coming forward, her head turned completely sideways, grinning and whimpering. Backed now into the farthest corner, the dog reared as if to avoid something that troubled him to such agony that he seemed to be rising from the floor; then he stopped, clawing sideways at the wall, his forepaws lifted and sliding, looking at her, striking against the wall, like a little horse; like something imploring a bird. Then as she, now head down, dragging her forelocks in the dust, struck against his side, he let loose one howl of misery and bit at her, dashing about her, barking, and as he sprang on either side of her he always kept his head toward her, dashing his rump now this side, now that, of the wall.
                    Then she began to bark also, crawling after him--barking in a fit of laughter, obscene and touching. The dog began to cry then, running with her, head-on with her head, as if slowly and surely to circumvent her; soft and slow his feet went pad- ding. He ran this way and that, low down in his throat crying, and she grinning and crying with him; crying in shorter and shorter spaces, moving head to head, until she gave up, lying out, her hands beside her, her face turned and weeping; and the dog too gave up then, and lay down, his eyes bloodshot, his head flat along her knees.
                </span>
        
            </p>
        
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>